Guide to the Timothy Vedder letters, 1861 MS2201
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Timothy Vedder letters
1861
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2201
0.25 Linear Feet
Collection contains holograph letters signed to family members in New York and Connecticut. These letters describe Washington, including brief mention of Columbian College (now George Washington University); drills and training; frequent illness of soldiers; retreat of Union soldiers from 1st Battle of Bull Run; and guarding house of brother of James T. Jackson, killer of E.E. Ellsworth, first Union casuality of war. These letters date from June 25-Sept. 26 of 1861.
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open for research.
Historical or Biographical Note
Timothy Vedder was a Union soldier from New York, stationed at Camp Douglas in Washington, D.C. and at Arlington Heights, Va.
Collection Scope and Content
The collection contains holograph letters signed to family members in New York and Connecticut. These letters describe Washington, including brief mention of Columbian College (now George Washington University); drills and training; frequent illness of soldiers; retreat of Union soldiers from 1st Battle of Bull Run; and guarding house of brother of James T. Jackson, killer of E.E. Ellsworth, first Union casuality of war. These letters date from June 25-Sept. 26 of 1861.
Purchased by Gelman library 1989.
Collection Organization
Organized into one series.
Collection note
The transcriptions of the letters are not online yet, but are available upon request.
Personal narratives; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Bull Run, 1st Battle, 1861; Camp Douglas (Washington, D.C.); Washington (D.C.); Vedder, Timothy F.
- Letter, 06/25/1861 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  General note
  Letter to his parents, brothers, and sisters.
- Letter, 06/27/1861 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Letter to his parents.
- Letter, 07/04/1861 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Letter to his parents, sisters, and brothers.
- Letter, 07/16/1861 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letter, 07/18/1861 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Letter to his sister Nellie Vedder.
- Letter, 07/20/1861 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Letter to his parents, sisters, and brothers. Appears to be incomplete.
- Letter, 07/25/1861 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Letter, 07/25/1861 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Letter to Francis Vedder
- Letter, 07/27/1861 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Letter, 09/01/1861 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Letter to his sister Nellie.
- Letter, 09/04/1861 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Letter to his sister Helen Vedder.
- Letter, 09/08/1861 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Letter, 09/23/1861 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Letter to his sister.
- Letter, 09/26/1861 (Box 1, Folder 14)